Abhishek Singh

Email: abhisheksinghbiet@gmail.com — Mobile: +91 7829448484 — LinkedIn

Summary

Data Scientist with 7 years of experience specializing in building end-to-end data science solutions to drive business value. Possesses a deep background in software engineering. Experienced at creating regression and classification models, using predictive data modeling, and analyzing data mining algorithms to deliver insights and implement action-oriented solutions to complex problems. Demonstrated proficiency in managing and optimizing data processing, building APIs, and implementing NLP applications. Experience in credit risk modeling and familiarity with Generative AI using Large Language Models. Strong technical skills in Python, SQL, Azure, and relevant libraries/frameworks.

Experience

Data Scientist

Cipla, Mumbai, Maharashtra

Jan 2022 - Current

- Leveraged Machine Learning to provide a recommendation that increased the yield of products by 1-4%.
- Developed and deployed custom machine learning models, resulting in a 10-20% reduction in machine setup time.
- Developed a custom monitoring service to check the health of the pipeline using Azure logic app.
- Led the development of a Python automation package, streamlining the model creation process.
- Built an automated data pipeline (ETL) ingesting granulation/coating machine data for modeling, enabling data-driven insights.
- Developed data processing system using Azure Services, achieving a reduction in processing time.

Data Scientist

eClerx, Mumbai, Maharashtra

Sep 2020 - Dec 2021

- Integrated incoming data into the client's system by maintaining 99% data integrity and consistency by performing data cleaning and normalization through Python scripts and SQL queries.
- Automated file organization with a 95% accuracy ML-based document classification solution, saving 2-3 hours/week
- Developed an NLP application to automate resume entity extraction, improving candidate screening efficiency.
- Built and deployed an ML application for automated entity extraction from invoices, improving processing efficiency.
- Built APIs from scratch enabling person detection & entity recognition systems.

Software Engineer

Altisource Business Solutions Pvt Ltd, Bangalore, Karnataka

Sep 2012 - Dec 2015

• Developed features for a Loan Servicing system (RealSynergy) by implementing user stories, ensuring smooth user experience and efficient loan processing.

Technical Skills

- Languages: Python, C++, Scala, SQL, Bash
- Database: Microsoft SQL Server, PostgreSQL, Hive
- Libraries: Numpy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, MatPlotLib, Seaborn, Spacy, PySpark, Tensorflow, keras, Langchain
- Machine Learning: Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Naive Bayes, SVM, Random Forest, XGBoost, LightGBM
- Deep learning: Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN), Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN), LSTM, Attention Mechanism, Transformer
- Web Frameworks: Flask, Django

- Tools: PyCharm, Airflow, Microsoft VS Code, Jupyter Notebook, Git
- Bug Tracking Tools: JIRA, Bugzilla
- Cloud Services: Azure Databricks, Azure Blob storage, Azure DevOps, Azure Virtual Machines, Azure Data Factory, Azure AD
- Software Engineering Techniques: Scrum, Agile, Waterfall, Iterative

Education

- Master of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering; Dr. B.R. Ambedkar National Institute of Technology, Jalandhar, Punjab

 Aug. 2018 July. 2020
- Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering; Bundelkhand Institute of Engineering and Technology, Jhansi, Uttar Pradesh

 Aug. 2008 May. 2012